Edwin Bruce Story Papers, 1877-1909
Smith College Archives
Edwin Bruce Story Papers
1877-1909
Story, Edwin Bruce, 1849-1909
RG 42 UUID:e6f12dab-ef72-45d6-916f-e2f1821d593d
5 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of Music. Contains correspondence, lecture notes, manuscripts, and photographs.
Edwin Bruce Story was born on May 15, 1849 in Gloucester, Massachusetts. His interest in music developed early and was encouraged by his mother. By the age of 14, he was the organist at a church in Gloucester. He studied piano and organ under Dr. B.C. Blodgett, William H. Sherwood, and Junius Hill. For five years Story was the organist at the Main Street Baptist Church in Worcester, Massachusetts. He was married to Helen B. Robbins Story and had two daughters, Marion and Helen, Class of 1900. In 1879, the family settled in Northampton, Massachusetts. That same year, Story became an assistant to Dr. B.C. Blodgett, who headed the music department at Smith College. In 1903 he became a full professor of music in the department. In addition to his work at Smith College, Story was the organist for the Second Congregational Church of Holyoke, Massachusetts starting in 1880. The following year Story was the organist and choir director of the Edwards Church in Northampton, beginning a twenty-five year position there. He also taught music classes at the Burnham School and Elms College. He was a talented composer who wrote and performed musical programs and concerts throughout his career. Edwin Bruce Story died suddenly on July 24, 1909 at his summer home in East Gloucester, Massachusetts. In honor of his accomplishments and service, a memorial service program was held at the Assembly Hall at Smith College on October 27, 1909.
The papers of Edwin Bruce Story include correspondence, lecture notes, manuscripts, memorial service materials, and photographs although the primary focus is on musical publications and programs. Although the collection is weak in correspondence, it does include a letter written by his daughter Helen Story, Class of 1900, regarding Edwin Bruce Story's musical work and discusses at least one of her father's programs. The collection also contains several photographs of Story and one photograph of his wife and his two daughters. Researchers may be interested in reading Story's hand-written lecture notes (topics include church music and the structure of the organ, 1899-1903). Researchers may also find the programs and newspapers that Story saved in 4 scrapbooks between 1877-1909 to be very insightful. There is a heavy concentration on Story's published work, especially on religious hymns and songs. The collection also contains several manuscripts, including songs arranged, composed, and/or written by Story.
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The Edwin Bruce Story papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Additional material is available at the Werner Josten Music Library at Smith College.
- Content list, obituary and memorial service 1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters and invitations 1905, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Lecture notes: Development of Church Music undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lecture notes: Meaning of the Mass 1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Lecture notes: Music of the Church of England 1903 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Lecture notes: The Structure of the Organ 1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs ca.1882-96, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Publications: Advent Christmas Cantata 1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Publications: Chronological Chart of Composers 1884-1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Publications: Five Hymn Anthems undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Publications: Good Bye undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Publications: Hymns undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Publications: Short Openings Anthems 1892 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Publications: Sketches from Pontoosuc undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Publications: Spring undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Publications: Technical Exercises 1886 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Publications: When the Wind Blows undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Music, Manuscripts: After undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Music, Manuscripts: At Last 1901 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Music, Manuscripts: Brightest and Best 1889-1902 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Music, Manuscripts: Cradle undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Music, Manuscripts: Christmas Cantana 1890-1903, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Music, Manuscripts: Day is Gently Sinking to a Close 1887-89, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Music, Manuscripts: Easter 1881-1903, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Music, Manuscripts: Hills of God undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Music, Manuscripts: In the Cross undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Music, Manuscripts: Music manuscripts 1890-1902, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Music, Manuscripts: A Little Old Woman undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Music, Manuscripts: Only 1878, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Music, Manuscripts: Organ and piano 1891-1900, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Music, Manuscripts: Tho O Lord, Art Our Father undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Music, Manuscripts: Under Starry Skies undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Music: Lutheran church service undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Music, General: Richard Strauss 1894, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Music, General: George Coleman Gow 1884-94 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Scrapbook 1877-91 (Box OV)
- Scrapbook 1891-1908 (Box OV)
- Scrapbook 1903-07 (Box OV)
- Scrapbook 1907-09 (Box OV)